Good חודש, Chodesh, today's דף Daf is ל"ו. Lamed Vav. We will,
God willing, be beginning a new פרק Perek very soon. But we
continue on the bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב' Lamed He Amud Bet
and we are dealing with a משנה. Mishna. We went from dealing
with אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik to שור המזיק, Shor Hamazik, the classic
case of שור תם Shor Tam in the תורה, Torah, splitting the
live ones, splitting the dead one. How they have to be dealing
with ox of equal value. Then we went to a little bit
of a digression or whatever, I don't know if you'd call it
a digression, anyway, separate topic of קים ליה. Kim Lei. Now we're
doing the topic of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya.
And where there's a debate about which ox gored or whose ox
gored and so on. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says that
although the משנה Mishna says המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi Mechavero Alav
Haraya, that the ניזק Nizak who wants to claim that it was
the higher liability has the burden of proof, this goes against סומכוס,
Sumchos, because סומכוס Sumchos would say whenever there's an objective doubt, you
split it. And the גמרא Gemara wanted to know if סומכוס Sumchos
would say this even when the מזיק Mazik is saying ברי, Bari,
even when the person you're trying to extract the money from is
saying yes, I definitely do not owe you the money, would סומכוס
Sumchos still say you split? And would this and is this opinion
in the משנה Mishna really
would oppose סומכוס? Sumchos? And the גמרא Gemara says yes, סומכוס Sumchos
would say you split if there's an objective ספק Safek even in
a case of ברי וברי. Bari Ve'bari. And the משנה Mishna is
a case of ברי וברי Bari Ve'bari because it's clear from the
way they're saying it. This happened. No, that happened. לאו כי. Loki.
So anyway, it's clear everybody is making a definite claim. We don't
know if they're lying or not, but it doesn't matter. They're making
a definite claim and סומכוס Sumchos would say the משנה Mishna says
המוציא מחברו Hamotzi Mechavero and סומכוס Sumchos would say חולקים. Chokim. But
then the גמרא Gemara turned to the question of one minute, if
everybody is saying ברי, Bari, then why do you have to pay
the lesser amount? The ניזק Nizak says the מזיק Mazik says it
was my תם Tam that damaged or it was my small ox
that damaged, my small תם. Tam. And the מזיק Mazik says no,
you're lying, it was the מועד Muad that damaged or it was
the ניזק Nizak saying the מזיק Mazik says it was a small
one or it was the תם Tam and the ניזק Nizak says
no, you're lying, it was the big one or it was the
מועד. Muad. So
it says, well, okay, he can't the ניזק Nizak can't prove it
was the larger liability, but the implication is but at least he
collects based on what the מזיק Mazik says. But the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, if he's saying to the מזיק Mazik no you're
lying, then he's rejecting the מזיק'ס Mazik's own admission. So he should
get nothing. And this is the principle of טענו בחיטין והודה לו
בשעורין Tano Bechitin Ve'hodo Lo Bise'orin that you're פטור. Patur. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, let's pick up with that. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay. הלא מייתי ראיה, Halo Maiti Raya, so
we will pick up about eight lines before the lines get wide.
הלא מייתי ראיה, Halo Maiti Raya, if you don't bring a proof,
שקיל כדאמר מזיק, Shakil Kedamar Mazik, so then you should take at
least according to what the מזיק Mazik concedes to. And if we're
talking about a ברי וברי Bari Ve'bari that everybody is saying no,
you're lying, no, you're lying, then נימא דתהוי תיובתא דרבה בר נתן.
Nema Dehavei Tyuvta DeRava Bar Natan. רבה בר נתן, Rava Bar Natan,
let's say this is a contradiction to רבה בר נתן, Rava Bar
Natan, דאמר, Damar, because רבה בר נתן Rava Bar Natan says טענו
חיטין והודה לו בשעורין, Tano Chitin Ve'hodo Lo Bise'orin, if I say
you owe me wheat and you say no, you're lying, I only
owe you barley, פטור, Patur, you don't even have to pay me
barley because I'm saying you don't owe me barley, you only owe
me wheat, so I'm rejecting your claim, so you're completely exempt.
Alright, so could it be it's different because those barley and wheat
are different things and money and money is it's more money or
less money. That would be if we were arguing about a מועד
Muad obligation. But if we're arguing about a שור תם Shor Tam
obligation, they really are different things, this animal or that animal. At
least that's the way the גמרא Gemara says.
My animal killed your animal.
There's both admitting that you owe me money, just that you borrowed
something from me, just because if you borrowed wheat or you borrowed
barley. But no, you do have to make it that it's not
just a question of how much, right? Presumably the issue is not
just the circumstances of the debt, but what is actually being admitted
in terms of what is owed. So if it's just a difference
of two hundred or a hundred even if they were arguing about
different circumstances, then you're still conceding to a hundred. Then when I'm
saying when that then you know my claim of two hundred still
includes the idea that you owe me a hundred. But it seems
here that the issue is that because it's a שור תם, Shor
Tam, if it was a מועד, Muad, I think it would not
be similar, but because it's a שור תם Shor Tam it is
seen as a type of a חיטין ושעורין Chitin Ve'se'orin because we're
arguing which ox I have a right to. Okay, but it's a
good question. But yes, that seems to be the point. So the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. אלא בברי ושמא. Ela Bevbari Veshema. Fine. So in order that
the משנה Mishna doesn't contradict this idea of חיטין ושעורין, Chitin Ve'se'orin,
we're not talking about a ברי וברי, Bari Ve'bari, we're talking about
a ברי ושמא. Bari Veshema. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say
what does that mean? Okay. דקאמר ברי מאן דקאמר שמא מאן. Dekamar
Bari Man Dekamar Shema Man. Who's saying ברי Bari and who's saying
שמא? Shema? Who's saying you definitely and who's saying no it's maybe?
אינימא דקאמר ניזק ברי. Inima Dekamar Nizak Bari. The ניזק Nizak is
saying you definitely owe me the bigger amount, it was definitely the
big cow,
it was the big ox, it was definitely the מועד. Muad. ודקאמר
מזיק שמא. Vedekamar Mazik Shema. The מזיק Mazik says I don't know,
maybe. Maybe it was the small one. So if that's true, okay,
אכתי לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבה בר נתן? akati leima tehevei tiyuvta de-Rabba
bar Natan? So then that should still be a case of חטין
ושעורין, chitin u-se'orin, because the ניזק nizak is saying you definitely do
not owe me the small one, you definitely owe me the big
one. So if that's true, then he shouldn't be able to collect
anything. He can't collect the big one because he can't prove it,
and he can't collect the small one because he's rejecting his claim
on the small one. So if the ניזק nizak is making is
saying the ברי, bari, then he shouldn't be allowed ironically he shouldn't
be allowed to collect anything. So אלא דקאמר ניזק שמא. ela de-ka'mar
nizak shema. The ניזק nizak is saying I don't know. The ניזק
nizak is saying you say, Mr. מזיק, mazik, that it was definitely
the small one. I don't know, maybe it was the big one.
So that case, okay, he doesn't המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה ha-motzi mi-chavero
alav ha-ra'ayah because obviously not only can he not prove that it
was the big one, he's not even certain it was the big
one. But at least he gets to collect based on what the
מזיק mazik says. Since he's saying you say the small, I don't
know, maybe it was the big, he's not rejecting the מזיק's mazik's
claim. So at least he's entitled to collect what the מזיק mazik
says. Okay, דקאמר ניזק שמא וקאמר מזיק ברי. de-ka'mar nizak shema ve-ka'mar
mazik bari.
So wait, so if he actually really did reject the מזיק's mazik's
claim, wouldn't get anything.
If it was a ברי וברי bari u-bari and they were arguing
about which שור תם, shor tam, then it would be a חטין
ושעורין chitin u-se'orin and he wouldn't get anything. That is what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. Okay, no, according to this idea of חטין
ושעורין, chitin u-se'orin, this רבה בר חנא. Rabba bar Chana. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara is דקאמר ניזק שמא וקאמר מזיק ברי. de-ka'mar nizak
shema ve-ka'mar mazik bari. So the ניזק nizak is saying maybe it's
the big one. מזיק mazik is saying no, it's definitely the small
one. So in that case, he gets to at least he collects
what the מזיק mazik says.
ומדסיפא ניזק שמא מזיק ברי, u-mi-de-seifa nizak shema mazik bari, since that
case the ניזק nizak is שמא shema and the מזיק mazik is
ברי, bari, רישא נמי ניזק שמא מזיק ברי. reisha nami nizak shema
mazik bari. So the רישא reisha also is that the ניזק nizak
is שמא shema and the מזיק mazik is ברי. bari. The ניזק
nizak is saying, you know,
maybe
it was your cow, and he says no, it definitely was on
the rock. Okay. So or like any of the earlier cases. ואמר
סומכוס אפילו בהא דאיצטריכא לאשמועינן דלא? ve-amar Sumchus afilu be-ha de-itztericha le-ashmi'inan
de-lo? Would סומכוס Sumchus say even in that case you say חולקין?
cholkin? Because here's the examples, right? Okay.
So basically, okay, let's say it's a case about like I don't
know, you've got the big one, okay, and you've got that's my
that's my very you like my modern art, and the small one,
okay. This is what so these are the מזיק mazik and here
you got the dead cow of the ניזק. nizak. Okay, looks like
a cockroach. Anyway, anyway, anyway, okay, so if the case is
if the if the ניזק nizak is saying I'm trying to think
about how to illustrate this. Anyway, if if the מזיק mazik is
saying it was ברי, bari, it was definitely this one. And that's
what the מזיק mazik is saying, okay, it was definitely the small
one. And the ניזק nizak is saying no, it was definitely it's
ברי, bari, it was definitely the big one, okay. If that's their
debate, right, so then the גמרא's Gemara's saying is he doesn't even
get the small one, right, because he's rejecting his claim that he
owes the small one. So in order for him to be entitled
to the small one, okay, it he can't be rejecting this claim,
he has to say שמא. shema. So since he's saying שמא, shema,
he says I don't know, maybe it was this, maybe it was
that, that at least entitles him to the small one. That's what
we said, okay. So that's how it's not a it's not a
חטין ושעורין chitin u-se'orin case. But remember, we're also trying to figure
out whether סומכוס Sumchus would disagree with this case. All right. So
in this case, right, if the ניזק nizak himself, the one who's
demanding the larger one, is uncertain of his claim, he doesn't know,
do I get the big one, do I get the small one
or whatever, he's uncertain of his claim and this guy is the
מוחזק, muchzak, right? The מזיק mazik is the מוחזק. muchzak. He's the
one that has it in his possession. He's coming to take it
away from the מזיק. mazik. So you're uncertain of your claim, he's
the מוחזק, muchzak, would סומכוס Sumchus really say חולקין cholkin in this
case? Right? It's one thing if neither if both of them are
שמא, shema, or if both of them are a ברי. bari. Everybody
says they don't know, or everybody says they do know. Then סומכוס
Sumchus might say fine, even though you're a מוחזק muchzak we're going
to split it. But here you're the מוחזק muchzak and you're saying
ברי, bari, and you're trying to take it away from this guy's
trying to take it away and he's saying שמא. shema. In that
case, would סומכוס Sumchus really say חולקין? cholkin? That's quite an extreme.
Okay. So what and why are we and we're claiming that סומכוס
Sumchus argues on our משנה, mishna, and סומכוס Sumchus would say חולקין
cholkin on our משנה.
mishna. So but he says, can't you say isn't this also a
case of כסף המוטל בספק? kesef ha-mutal be-safek?
Right, so the גמרא Gemara said that we started the סוגיא sugya
by saying it was. And now the גמרא's Gemara's saying but now
because of חטין ושעורין, chitin u-se'orin, we have to say that the
ניזק nizak is saying שמא, shema, can you still say that סומכוס
Sumchus would say חולקין cholkin in this case?
So what's to prevent this מזיק mazik from always lying?
Nothing, absolutely nothing. In the same thing nothing to prevent the ניזק
nizak from always lying.
No he can't, because if he says
ברי bari he might lose. That's true, yep, life's unfair. No you're
right, it's true, that's part of the aspects of מוחזק. muchzak. Right.
Okay.
Right. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Where are we? למימרא דסיפא
ניזק שמא
ומזיק ברי רישא נמי ניזק שמא ומזיק ברי ואמר סומכוס אפילו בהא
דאיכא למשמע דלא וסומכוס הכא נמי פליג?
Lememra deseifa Nezak shema uMazik
bari reisha nami Nezak shema uMazik bari ve'amar Sumchus afilu beha de'ika
lemashma delo veSumchus hacha nami palig? Would סומכוס Sumchus say in this
case חולקים? Cholkim? That you'd have to say oh, this is going
against סומכוס? Sumchus? Gemara says לא. Lo. סיפא ניזק שמא ומזיק ברי.
Seifa Nezak Shema uMazik Bari. The end case, one of the later
cases, we don't really have to worry what's the end and what's
the beginning, you know, because just a lot of different examples. Okay,
one of the cases is a ניזק שמא ומזיק ברי, Nezak Shema
uMazik Bari, that's this case. And that would tell you that you're
entitled to the smaller amount because you're not rejecting his claim. רישא
ניזק ברי ומזיק שמא. Reisha Nezak Bari uMazik Shema. But we could
also be talking in the beginning, again, it's a different scenario of
them arguing but we're not going to worry about that. But we
could also be talking in a different scenario about the
ניזק Nezak saying ברי, Bari, it's definitely was your larger one, and
the מזיק Mazik saying oh I don't know, maybe it was my
larger one, maybe it was the smaller one. Okay, so in this
case, all the more that סומכוס Sumchus could say חולקים. Cholkim. You're
making a definite claim, the guy who has it in his possession
isn't even certain. So in that case where the ברי Bari and
the שמא Shema flip, there is a very strong reason to say
חולקים. Cholkim. Okay, and that's why סומכוס Sumchus at least in a
case
of ברי וברי Bari uBari presumably סומכוס Sumchus would say חולקים, Cholkim,
and certainly in a case of the ניזק Nezak saying ברי Bari
and the guy who's מוחזק Muchzak saying שמא, Shema, סומכוס Sumchus would
say חולקים. Cholkim. And our משנה Mishna is telling you even in
this case, which is such a good reason to say חולקים, Cholkim,
it's an objective ספק, Safek, and the מוחזק Muchzak is saying a
שמא, Shema, even in that case our משנה Mishna is saying המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. This is the best case
for סומכוס Sumchus to say חולקים, Cholkim, right? Because the guy who's
making, who's trying to take out the money, it's an objective ספק
Safek and he's making a definite claim. The guy in whose possession
of the money is making a doubtful claim. So that's a case
where there's a lot of logic to say חולקים, Cholkim, a lot
of logic to agree with סומכוס. Sumchus. And our משנה Mishna tells
you you always say המוציא מחברו. Hamotzi mechavero. Okay, so the משנה
Mishna has two cases. In a case where the מוחזק Muchzak is
saying a שמא, Shema, it's telling you you would have wanted to
say like סומכוס Sumchus חולקים, Cholkim, no, I'm telling you the הלכה
Halacha is המוציא מחברו. Hamotzi mechavero. And in the case where this
guy is the שמא, Shema, it's telling you he doesn't lose his
claim, he at least gets to do what the מזיק Mazik says
because it's not a חיטים ושעורים Chittin uSe'orim case. Wait, let me
just finish reading this. Okay. Okay, סיפא ניזק שמא ומזיק ברי רישא
ניזק ברי ומזיק שמא. Seifa Nezak Shema uMazik Bari Reisha Nezak Bari
uMazik Shema. והא לא דמיא רישא לסיפא. Veha lo damya Reisha leSeifa.
The רישא Reisha doesn't... isn't similar to the סיפא. Seifa. So אמרי,
Amri, because one is a ברי ושמא Bari veShema and the other
is a שמא וברי. Shema uBari. אמרי, Amri, no, you could say
ברי ושמא שמא וברי חדא מילתא היא. Bari veShema Shema uBari chada
milta hi. No, our משנה Mishna is talking about different scenarios about...
I mean, but they're all the same genre. One person is saying
ברי Bari and one is saying שמא, Shema, it just reverses who
is saying what.
חדא מילתא היא. Chada milta hi. ברי וברי שמא וברי תרי מילי
נינהו. Bari uBari Shema uBari trei milei ninhu. But we could not
say that part of the משנה Mishna is talking about ברי וברי
Bari uBari and part is שמא וברי. Shema uBari. That would actually
be two different genres, going from everybody making a definite claim to
people making doubtful claims. But if the משנה Mishna is talking about
different scenarios of people making doubtful claims, then we can flip who
is saying what. Okay, so again what the גמרא Gemara has done
was in order to allow the implication being that you're allowed to
collect at least based on what the מזיק Mazik says, it has
to be that the ניזק Nezak is making a שמא Shema claim.
So part of the משנה Mishna which is implying that the ניזק
Nezak can collect based on what the מזיק Mazik says is that
the ניזק Nezak is only making a שמא Shema claim. In order
to sustain the argument that our משנה Mishna is making a point
of rejecting סומכוס, Sumchus, we're going to flip it and say there's
cases in the משנה Mishna where the מזיק... Mazik where the ניזק
Nezak is saying ברי Bari and the מזיק Mazik is saying שמא,
Shema, where there would be a really good reason to go like
סומכוס Sumchus חולקים, Cholkim, and nevertheless we're not. We're going to say
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
And then if he doesn't bring a ראיה, raya, he gets what
the מזיק Mazik says?
And if he doesn't bring a ראיה raya and it was a
case where the ניזק nizak said ברי Bari and the מזיק Mazik
said שמא, Shema, okay, then... and then he is... well no, because
wait a minute, if... that's an interesting question, if the מזיק Mazik
is saying שמא, Shema, I don't know if that would be a
טענו חיטים והודה לו בשעורים Ta'ano chittin vehoda lo bise'orim because he's...
the מזיק Mazik is saying maybe this maybe that. So he's... the
מזיק Mazik is rejecting the ניזק'ס Nezak's claim about this, but the
מזיק Mazik hasn't denied the possibility that it might be that. Right,
you're stuck between רב נתן Rav Natan and סומכוס Sumchus in
that case.
Yeah,
it could be in this case you're right, it could be he
gets nothing because he's rejecting the concession about the smaller and he
can't prove the bigger. But the מזיק mazik isn't really denying the
bigger either. So I'm not exactly sure, I don't exactly know what
the הלכה Halacha would be in that case. Okay, let's take... Let's
take a look now as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. גופא *Gufa*.
אמר *Amar*,
let's go back to the חטים *chittim* and שעורים *se'orim* case. אמר
רבה בר נתן *Amar Rabbah bar Natan*, טענו חטים והודו לו בשעורים
פטור *tanu chittim v'hodu lo bi-se'orim patur*. Okay, מאי קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan *mai ka mashma lan*? What does this teach us?
It's a big חדוש *chiddush*, right? That you don't even collect the
שעורים *se'orim*, but point is we've learned it elsewhere. תנינא *Tanina*, we
taught a ברייתא Braita *braita*. טענו חטים והודו לו בשעורים פטור *tanu
chittim v'hodu lo bi-se'orim patur*. Okay, it's an explicit teaching. What did
he say that we didn't already hear? אי מהתם הוה אמינא פטור
מדמי חטים וחייב בדמי שעורים *ee me-hatam hava amina patur midmei chittim
v'chayav bidmei se'orim*. No, I would have just thought it meant you're
not allowed to collect the חטים *chittim*, which is pretty obvious because
like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-raaya. *hamotzi me-chavero alav
ha-reaya*. But at least you have to pay what you conceded to,
at least the value of the שעורים *se'orim*. קא משמע לן דפטור
לגמרי *ka mashma lan de-patur legamri*. You're completely exempt because the guy
who says חטים *chittim* was rejecting the claim of שעורים *se'orim*. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says like this. תנן *Tnan*. היו המזיקין שנים,
אחד גדול ואחד קטן *hayu ha-mazikin shnayim, echad gadol v'echad katan*. Okay,
this was, you know, my picture on the board. Oh no, this
is the נזיקין *nezikin* where the killed animals were two, a big
one and a small one. הלא מייתי ראיה *hala mayti reaya*. We're
back to what we said. If he did, you know, it's המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-raaya *hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-reaya*. I'm
trying to say that you owe me for the big one, your
big one killed my big one, etc. You say it's the opposite.
I have to prove it. Okay. הלא מייתי ראיה *hala mayti reaya*.
If I can't prove it, שקל כדאמר מזיק mazik *shakal k'de-amar mazik*.
At least I get to collect based on what you the מזיק
mazik *mazik* conceded. אמאי *Amai*? חטים ושעורים נינהו *chittim v'se'orim ninhu*. It's
a חטים *chittim* and שעורים *se'orim* similar to exactly what we said
before. Now a minute ago we said the answer was ברי bari
ושמא *bari v'shema*. Okay, that I didn't say you definitely owe me
the big one, I said you might owe me the big one.
Here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is doing a different answer. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* figure out why it's doing a different
answer here, but here's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s different answer. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is ראוי ליטול ואין לו *ra'ui litol v'ein lo*.
It says, you know what, you're right. Meaning, if you say, I
say it was the bigger one and you say it's the smaller
one, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. *hamotzi me-chavero alav
ha-reaya*. I have to prove to you it's the bigger one. And
if I can't prove to you it's the bigger one, I really
should be entitled to the smaller one because that's at least what
you're conceding, but I can't get it because I've admitted that it's
not the smaller one. So ואין לו *v'ein lo*. So here's a
different read. I know, but here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading that
in the case of the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*, when they're debating and
we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-reaya*, what it's
really saying is the ניזק nizak *nizak* gets nothing. Right. You have
to prove it's the larger one. Since you can't prove it's the
larger one, then you really should be getting the smaller one, that's
what the other guy is conceding, but you already rejected that claim,
so נבך *nebach*, you get nothing. You should be getting, but you
don't get. Now we'll see in a minute that there's a way
in which you can get it.
Is this a case of both ברי *bari*'s?
Both ברי *bari*'s. So rather than giving the answer that our משנה
Mishna *Mishnah*'s talking about a ברי ושמא *bari v'shema*, you're right, it's
not disagreeing with the פסק *psak*. Rather than having the משנה Mishna,
*Mishnah* case where you get it because you said a שמא *shema*,
we're reading the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* that you said a ברי *bari*
and we're consistent and we're saying נבך *nebach* you don't get anything.
You said a ברי *bari* and therefore you don't get anything. ראוי
ואין לו *Ra'ui v'ein lo*. והתניא *Ve-hatanya*, but we taught in a
ברייתא *braita*. הרי זה משתלם על הקטן מן הגדול ועל הגדול מן
הקטן *harei zeh mishtalem al ha-katan min ha-gadol v'al ha-gadol min ha-katan*.
But the ברייתא *braita* says no, you do get based on the
smaller concession, on what the מזיק Mazik *mazik* conceded. You know, you
collect for your big one from the small ox and your small
one from the big ox. פשט דתפס detafas. *Pshat de-tafas*. Ah, that's
different. There, you actually seized the property. So there you sort of
switched around who the מוחזק muchzak. *muchzak* is. Okay. So you actually
took possession of it and there at least you're entitled to get
based on your smaller claim. Now I have to tell you, I
really don't understand this, because if it's a case that's תפס tafas.
*tafas*, then maybe I should even be able to keep even my
larger claim if I'm switching around who the מוחזק *muchzak* is, which
raises a whole interesting question which I'm not going to get into,
which is, you know, can, when we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
*hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-reaya*, I say you owe me a thousand dollars,
you say no I don't, I have the burden of proof. If
it's sort of like an עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה *avid inish dina
l'nafsheih*, if I sneak into your house and I take your nice
big screen TV which is worth a thousand dollars, I know where
you're putting your money and I take a thousand dollars. Okay, and
now I say oh, now I'm the מוחזק *muchzak*. You have to
prove it from me. Okay. What happens if like, would that be
true? Or if people witnessed me stealing it, then do we have
to say no, no, no, you're not a מוחזק *muchzak*, now you're
a גנב *ganav*, give it back, right? Is it if I steal
it and nobody sees it? I mean, what is the scenario of
תפס *tafas* and does תפס *tafas* switch who's considered to be the
מוחזק *muchzak*? Okay. But if תפס *tafas* does switch who the מוחזק
*muchzak* is, then I should be able to keep even my larger
claim, right? 'Cause now I'm the מוחזק *muchzak* and you have to
prove to me the opposite. So it sounds like תפס *tafas* isn't
switching who the מוחזק *muchzak* is. You're not allowed to keep your
larger claim, but you're allowed to keep the smaller claim. But what's
the logic in that? Okay, if I admitted that you don't owe
me the smaller one, why does being תופס *tofes* switch things? So
it's a very strange גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, why תפס *tafas* actually works.
Okay, let's read a little bit more. תנן *Tnan*, we taught in
the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. היה אחד תם tam, ואחד מועד, muad. הניזק
אומר מועד muad. הזיק אחד הגדול ותם את הקטן והמזיק אומר לא
כי אלא תם tam, את הגדול ומועד את הקטן *haya echad tam
v'echad muad, ha-nizak omer muad hizik echad ha-gadol v'tam et ha-katan v'ha-mazik
omer lo ki ela tam et ha-gadol u-muad et ha-katan*. Okay, so
same similar idea, right? I'm saying that the מועד muad, *muad*, you
know, is the one that gored my big one and the תם
tam. *tam* is small and you say the reverse. המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה *hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-reaya*. You gotta bring the burden of proof.
הלא מייתי ראיה *hala mayti reaya*, again, it sounds like if you
didn't bring the proof, שקל כדאמר מזיק Mazik *shakal k'de-amar mazik*. At
least you'd get based on what the מזיק Mazik *mazik* conceded. אמאי
*Amai*? חטים ושעורים נינהו *chittim v'se'orim ninhu*. It's חטים *chittim* and שעורים
*se'orim*. So the גמרא Gemara's says again, ראוי לו ואין לו. Ra'ui
lo ve'ein lo. Yeah, you really don't get what the מזיק Mazik
admitted. You should be getting, but you get nothing because you basically
said he didn't owe you anything—you rejected his claim. והתניא הרי זה
משתלם מן הקטן מן המועד וגדול מן התם? Vehatanya harei ze mishtalem
min hakatan min hamuad vegadol min hatam? But the ברייתא says, you
collect based on at least the smaller claim. So it says again,
דתפס. You seized it. Okay, but again, if you seized it, collect
the larger claim. How does seizing it work here? Okay, now let's
take a look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot. clarifies it a little
bit. ראוי לו ואין לו, Ra'ui lo ve'ein lo, the second line
of תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says, okay, ודווקא היכא דיש לו תביעה
על שני השוורים על הגדול ועל הקטן אם תפס משתלם. Vedafka heicha
de'ish lo tvia al shnei hashavarim al hagadol veal hakatan im tafas
mishtalem. Okay, only if you have a claim on both of them.
You say, you owe me from the big one and the small
one, except I say you owe me a lot from the big
and a little from the small and you say the reverse. But
at least even according to my ברי claim, I'm not giving up
my right to both of your oxen. We're talking about different proportions,
but I'm continuing to claim both of your oxen, okay? Get that
case? אבל מתניתין דלעיל דאין לו תביעה אלא על הגדול אפילו תפס
הקטן אין משתלם מיניה. Aval matnitin deleil de'ein lo tvia ela al
hagadol afilu tafas hakatan ein mishtalem mineih. Okay, so
but he says, listen to this different scenario. Okay, in this case,
okay, I basically claim that if it's basically you say, I only
have rights to this, and I say I only have rights to
this, so I am denying that I have any rights to your
small one, right? Everybody with me? So grabbing the small one does
nothing for me. I've completely denied that I have rights to your
small one. How does grabbing it do it? But if we both
agree that I have rights to your big and your small, except
you say, I've got this much of your big and this much
of your small, and I say, no, no, no, I've got this
much of your big and only this much of your small, okay?
Everybody right get that? So in that case, okay, if I go
ahead and I grab, let's say, the small one, okay, then at
least I am or I don't know, I grab the big one,
okay, at least that's why תוספות Tosafot says if I go ahead
and I grab the big one, I don't get to keep the
whole, well, I grab both of them or whatever, I grab the
big one, I don't get to keep the whole amount based on
what I say, but at least I get to keep part of
it. If I grab the small one, I don't again, actually, I
would only get to keep the small part, but the point being
that in those cases where we're disagreeing about the proportions, now it
begins to make sense because I've never really rejected my ownership of
this or my ownership of that, right? Even within the claims I'm
making, there's an overlap here, right? Right,
you see the overlap of our claims? Okay, and that's why if
I grab it, I'm entitled to it. Of course, that's such a
good point that why should I need to grab it? Right? Since
even based on my claims, right, I'm not completely rejecting yours, in
both cases there's an overlap of our claims, I should at least
be entitled, right, you know, to like get the overlap. So I
still don't fully get it, but תוספות Tosafot is saying, grabbing doesn't
work. If you've really rejected your claim in that cow, then grabbing
it doesn't work. The only time grabbing works is if we're arguing
about the proportions of each ox, and in that case, since you
didn't completely reject your rights to that ox, you know, or basically
his concession of your rights, you're at least entitled to what you're
at least entitled to what he conceded. Okay, so I sort of
understand it better, but I still don't get then if that's true,
I still don't get why you need תפיסה, tefisa, right? If you
right, there's at least still an overlap. I don't get why you
need תפיסה tefisa and why תפיסה tefisa works, yes.
That the who has the burden of proof doesn't switch as to
which proportion which person gets.
Yeah, but if it did, then I should be able if I
grab the big one to keep the whole big one. But it
doesn't, it just says I get to keep the small one, right?
And if I grab the small one, it sounds like I get
based on what the מזיק conceded, it sounds like I get the
whole small one, even though I've really rejected eighty percent of the
small one, right? So I don't get it, like I get the
idea of the overlap, but I don't get then why like you
need the תפיסה. tefisa. I don't get what the תפיסה tefisa does
and if תפיסה tefisa works, then it should work even for the
entire claim. Alright, anyway, let's move on. At least we understand, what?
I don't know. Let's move on. היו שניהם לאיש אחד שניהם חייבים.
Hayu shneihem le'ish echad shneihem chayavim.
Now, we're going back to an earlier stage of the משנה. Mishna.
The earlier stage of the משנה Mishnah here is, here's my, here's
my dead cow. Okay, it still looks like a cockroach. Okay, and
here's your, you have two cows, they all look like cockroaches. I
don't know why, anyway. Anyway, here's your two cows, the small one
and a big one. Now, it says if one belonged to ראובן
Reuven and one belonged to שמעון, Shimon, then I can't collect from
either. Okay, because each one says, no, it was yours, right? But
and I can't prove either one, but if they both belong to
the same person, it says
שניהם חייבים. shneihem chayavim. Now, what does it mean they're both חייב?
chayav? We still don't know which one gored, right? We could say
then obviously you owe me. money, but actually it's an interesting question.
You owe me money but I don't know which cow I can
collect from, because if it's a תם, tam. I can only collect
from the cow, right? So yes you owe me money, so saying
שניהם חייבים shnayhem chayavim is not so clear what that means because
why anyway why not just say you're חייב, chayav, why שניהם חייבים?
shnayhem chayavim? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with that.
Okay. Okay. היו שניהם של איש אחד שניהם חייבים. Hayu shnayhem shel
ish echad shnayhem chayavim. אמר ליה רבא מפרזיקא לרב אשי שמע מינה
שוורים תמים שהזיקו, Amar leh Rava mi-Parzika le-Rav Ashi shema mina she-shvarim
tamim she-hiziku, if two oxen gored together רצה מזה גובה ורצה מזה
גובה. ratza mi-zeh goveh ve-ratza mi-zeh goveh.
So I can collect from either one. So you have two oxen
that gored my ox and let's say I can't collect from one
of the oxen ran away or whatever, I can collect from the
other one. It seems like they've done one big act of goring.
Okay, now the question is is that even if it's owned by
two separate people? Let's say Reuven and Shimon's ox both gore mine.
Okay, and then Reuven takes his ox and runs away. Can I
collect the full amount from Shimon? All right, so that seems to
be the scenario and the answer is yes. You don't view it
like Reuven did half and Shimon did half and you only have
half rights to Reuven and half rights to Shimon's. No, you view
them as they combined did the whole היזק. hezek. We're going to
see these scenarios later on, cases of like רצה מזה גובה ורצה
מזה גובה. ratza mi-zeh goveh ve-ratza mi-zeh goveh. If your ox pushes
my ox down a well, do I only collect half from the
owner of the well and half from the owner of the ox?
Let's say one of them can't be found. Can I collect all
from one from the other person? So it says if two oxen
gore, you view them as sort of operating in a unit and
if I need to I can collect all of them from one
ox. Okay, now.
And then Shimon and Reuven have to work it out between themselves.
It's not my problem.
Exactly, exactly. Now the point is fine, that's true if they both
would have gored you could really say שניהם חייבים. shnayhem chayavim. Okay,
but here the point is that there's a ספק safek which one
gored. We don't know, it's not that they both did, we don't
know which one did. But תוספות Tosafot says the גמרא's Gemara דיוק
diyuk is still from the fact that it uses the phrase שניהם
חייבים. shnayhem chayavim. That שניהם חייבים shnayhem chayavim is קא משמע לן
to indicate to me that in this case it's true they both
didn't do it, but there are cases where both oxen did it
and it would be that they would both share equally in the
obligation. So it's like a דיוק diyuk from the משנה, Mishna? not
the case of the משנה. Mishna? All right, we'll worry about it,
like we can't do everything. Okay, it's a דיוק diyuk from the
משנה, Mishna it's not the case in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so
הכא במאי עסקינן. hacha be-mai askinan. גמרא Gemara says no not necessarily,
what are we talking about here? במועדים. be-muadim. They're not a תם,
tam they're a מועד. muad. And that's why it says that שניהם
חייבים. shnayhem chayavim. One minute, the גמרא Gemara says אי במועדים אימא
סיפא, ei be-muadim eima seifa, can't be מועד. muad? It says, let's
look at the end. היה אחד גדול ואחד קטן הניזק אומר גדול
הזיק והמזיק אומר לא כי אלא קטן הזיק. haya echad gadol ve-echad
katan ha-nizak omer gadol hizik ve-ha-mazik omer lo ki ela katan hizik.
We're debating whether it was the big or the small one that
gored. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. אי במועדים, ei be-muadim, and if it's
a מועד, muad, מאי נפקא ליה מיניה? mai nafka leh minei? What
do I care if it's a big or a small one that
gored? סוף סוף דמי תרוייהו בעי לשלומי. sof sof dmei tarvayhu baei
leshalumei. You have to pay for the full damage. Clearly the fact
that we're debating it means that we're talking about a תם. tam
So the גמרא Gemara says no. סיפא בתמים ורישא במועדים. seifa be-tamim
ve-reisha be-muadim.
Fine, the end where we're debating big and small, that's a case
of תם. tam? But the beginning where we're talking about two oxen
and you don't know which one gored and we say שניהם חייבים,
shnayhem chayavim, that's that they're both מועד. muad, So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה אבחה סבא לרב אשי, amar leh Avacha Sava le-Rav
Ashi, אי במועדים, ei be-muadim, no can't be that they're מועדים. muadim.
חייבים, chayavim, why would it say they're both חייב? chayav? The oxen
are חייב. chayav. חייב גברא מיבעי ליה. chayav gavra miba'ei leh. It
should have said the owner has to pay. חייבים chayavim means that
I've got a right to the oxen. And פשיטא מאי שניהם, pashita
mai shnayhem, what does it mean both of them are חייב? chayav?
It should have just said the owner is חייב. chayav. אלא לעולם
בתמים, ela le-olam be-tamim, fine it's תמים, tamim, ורבי עקיבא היא. ve-Rabbi
Akiva hi.
Now what do we do by the phrase שניהם חייבים? shnayhem chayavim?
Again, because in this case it's really not true that שניהם חייבים.
shnayhem chayavim. It's really that one of them is חייב chayav and
we don't know which one. So the גמרא Gemara thought the point
of the phrase שניהם חייבים shnayhem chayavim is a דיוק diyuk that
when both of them do gore and you know both of them
gored, then each one is fully responsible and you could collect from
one if you can't collect from the other. But the גמרא's Gemara
rejecting that. That's not the point of saying שניהם חייבים. shnayhem chayavim.
Now before we get to the phrase שניהם חייבים, shnayhem chayavim, the
real question is: by the way, if this case even if they
both belong to Reuven and you don't know which one gored, why
are you allowed to collect anything? I say I have rights to
your bigger one, I have rights to this one, and Reuven says
no you don't, maybe you have rights to this one. I say
fine give me this one, no you don't maybe you have rights
to this one. Prove to me which one you have rights to
and I'll give it to you. Since you can't prove to me
which one you have rights to you don't get anything, right? Now
that already is an interesting question. If I know that I have—I
can prove that one of the VCRs—I don't know why I always
go to VCR because I figure like nobody has them nowadays—anyway, if
I know one of the laptop computers in your house is mine,
okay, but you have another identical one and I can't prove which
one is mine, do I basically get nothing? Do we say המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה or the fact that I know you've got one
of them means that at least you've got to give me one
or pay me for one even if I can't prove which one?
That's sort of like this case. I know I have rights to
one of your cows, I just can't prove which one. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara. says. אלא
לעולם בתמים ורבי עקיבא היא
דאמר שותפין נינהו. ela le-olam be-tamim ve-Rabbi Akiva hi de-amar shutfin ninhu.
It's Rabbi Akiva that says they're שותפין, shutfin, okay, וטעמא דאיתנהו לתרוייהו
ve-taama de-itnayhu le-tarvayhu and the reason I'm entitled to— out get paid
is because both of the oxen are around so I can say
one of them might is mine, or you know I have rights
to one of them, yes I don't know which one, but you
make up your mind. Give me at least one of them, you
know, clearly one of them is mine. So that's why if I
have both of them are still alive, you gotta pay me in
one way or another. Okay, דלא מצי מדחילה, de'lo matzi madcheila, you
can't push me off. אבל ליתנהו לתרוייהו, aval leitneihu letarvaihu, let's say
one of these oxen died, okay, and then I say pay me
what you owe me. I can't collect anything, cause you can say
maybe the one that died, that was yours. Okay? מצי אמר ליה
זיל אייתי ראיה דהאי תורא אזיקך ואשלם לך. matzi amar lei zil
ayisi raya de'hai tora azikach ve'ashallem lach. Go prove to me the
living one is still yours and I'll pay you. Since you can't,
you're out. So שניים חייבים shnaim chayavim doesn't mean I can collect
from both of them. It means that I need both of them
to be around to allow me to collect. One of them is
mine or I have rights to one of them, okay? And if
both of them are around, I can prove that you owe me
something and you'll have to pay me. But if one of them
is not alive, then I can't collect, cause maybe the one that
isn't around is mine and you can get out of paying. Yes.
How would I collect if both were around? If this did 200
dollars of damage, okay, and therefore I have a 100 dollar right
to one of them, I don't know, let's say everything is worth
200 dollars, okay?
In this case not, let's say one's a big one and it's
worth fifty.
Fine, it doesn't matter then you'll figure it out. Okay, if everything
is worth 200, I have a 100 dollar right to one of
them, I just don't know which one. So if both of them
are around, I could say I have a 100 dollars of property
in your possession, okay, you figure out which one it is you
want to give me, but you have 100 dollars of my property
in your possession. But if one of them is not around, one
of them died or ran away, then you'll say to me, 'I'm
not giving you any of this. I'm gonna assume the one that
ran away, that was yours.' And then המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Yes.
Someone's really reading שניים חייבים shnaim chayavim
as שניים מחייבים, shnaim mechayavim, in other words, you need both there.
Right, well something like that. Yeah, okay, right, right. מה? ma?
Now, earlier in the סוגיא, sugya, what difference does it make if
they're תם Tam. or מועד? muad. What difference does that make?
Because if it's מועד, then it wouldn't matter if it was a
small one or a big one that damaged, I get full damages.
The owner would still
be different, right? No, oh yes, no, but if they were both
מועדים, muadim, then we wouldn't be debating which one did the damage.
If both of your oxen are מועד, wouldn't it matter?
A small one and a big one?
Yeah, cause then you you just pay full damages. Oh my...
The מזיק size doesn't matter, the ניזק nizak size matters.
Right, and I was about to ask you
what happens if they're different. I understand, but let's I... Okay, let's
get some basics down. Now I want to take a look at
a short תוספות Tosafot. which is very important in the רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael debate. Cause why does the
גמרא Gemara say this is רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, right? Let's say
it's רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, shouldn't it be the same issue that
I need both around? Here becomes a very key question. According to
רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, if you don't have your ox around, remember
we said according to רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael I have like a
focused lien on your ox and if you sell it I can
collect it from a third party? Let's say the ox is no
longer around. Can you say, 'I'm not paying you cash, your lien
is only on my ox'? How much can you do that? How
much do I need the ox around in order to entitle me
to, you know, my fundamental right starts with my ox? Like you
could buy me off, you could say, 'Yes, you have a right
to the ox, but I'll pay you cash to buy you off.'
But if I come to you and I say, 'I don't want
your ox, I want your cash,' are you allowed to say, 'Tough
luck, buddy'? Even according to רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, your basic right
is to my ox. I might be able to pay you off
and you know, and and give you cash if I chose to
do it, but your right starts with fundamental right to my ox.
So here's a big נפקא מינא: nafka mina: according to רבי ישמעאל,
Rebbi Yishmael, my ox that gored your ox dies, okay, can you
collect any money from me? Okay, do we say yes, cause I
still owe you money, or we say no, even though it's not
an ownership that you have in my ox, it's a debt, the
debt primarily is on a right to collect from the ox. So
let's look at this תוספות. Tosafot רבי עקיבא דאמר שותפין נינהו, Rebbi
Akiva de'amar shutfin ninhu, פירוש בקונטרס דלרבי ישמעאל
דאמר בעל חוב הוא וזוזי הוא דמצי דחי,
pirush bekuntres de'leRebbi
Yishmael de'amar ba'al hov hu vezuzei hu de'matzi dachei, according to רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael that it's a debt, so אם עבר אחד לא
איבד זכותו. im avar echad lo ibbed zechuto. So רש"י Rashi, says,
your, you,
the ניזק's nizak right is not limited to the lien on the
ox. So according to רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, if one of them
ran away, I'd still be able to get my money from you.
So you're telling me it's my ox that ran away, what if
it was my ox that ran away? I don't want to collect
from the ox. You owe me 100 dollars, pay me 100 dollars,
I don't have to collect from the ox, it's just a lien
I have on the ox. So according to רש"י, Rashi, very important,
according to רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael my rights are not limited just
to that ox. But תוספות Tosafot disagree. וקשיא דלעיל אמר אפילו רבי
ישמעאל שחטו מה שעשה עשוי. vekashya de'le'eil amar afilu Rebbi Yishmael shachto
mah she'asah asui. The גמרא Gemara, says according to רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi
Yishmael, if you shechted the goring ox, the ניזק nizak is out
his money. So תוספות Tosafot says very reasonably, why is the ניזק
nizak out his money? Let the ניזק Nizak say, 'Fine, you shechted
it, it's not worth as much, pay me cash.' So תוספות Tosfos,
says the fact that the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, it sounds
like the ניזק Nizak does not have rights to collect from anything
other than... the ox. The מזיק can buy him off, but the
ניזק's Nizak rights are limited to collect from the ox. And that's
why if the ox died, the ניזק is out money. So if
an ox ran away, the מזיק would say to him, 'Yeah, the
one that ran away, that was yours. Yes, I owe you a
hundred dollars, but your lien is totally on the ox. And that's
the one that ran away, so I'm sorry, I'm not giving you
anything.' So one minute. So it says וניראה לפרש דמשום הכי מוקי
כרבי עקיבא U-nireh le-faresh de-mishum hachi moki ke-Rabbi Akiva משום דרבי
ישמעאל אין שום חידוש. mishum de-Rabbi Yishmael ein shum chidush. It's obvious
דפשיטא דאיבד זכותו כשיאבד האחר de-pishita de-ibed zechuto k'she-yaved ha-acher כיון דבעל
חוב הוא. kivan de-ba'al chov hu. According to Rabbi Yishmael, it's obvious
if one ran away, you're out because I could say, 'Yeah, yours
was the one that ran away and you have the lien on
it.' אבל לרבי עקיבא דשותפין נינהו, Aval le-Rabbi Akiva de-shutfin ninhu, סלקא
דעתך אמינא כאילו אחד משנים בחזקת הניזק. sal-ka dach-tach amina ke-ilu echad
mi-shenayim be-chezkat ha-nizak. But he says maybe
according to Rabbi Akiva, we would think the idea of חזקה Chazaka
changes. Since I already own it, maybe even if one ran away,
maybe I have a חזקה Chazaka this one because if it's mine,
maybe I'm considered a מוחזק. Okay, so I don't want to sort
of get into that. But the basic point I want us to
appreciate is that according to רשי, Rashi there's a debate of רשי
Rashi, and תוספות, Tosfos, a very critical debate. For Rabbi Yishmael that
says that you owe me money and I have a lien on
your ox, can I if the ox isn't around, can I still
collect? According to רשי, Rashi the answer is yes, fundamentally you owe
me money. And according to תוספות, Tosafot the answer is no. Yes,
you owe me money, but my whole all of my rights are
limited to the right to collect that money from the ox. I
don't have a lien on any of your other property. Jonathan, you
had a question?
Is there a difference between Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Akiva?
No, because the difference would still be that's why the גמרא Gemara
said that one נפקא מינה Nafka mina would be... are there still
נפקא מינה's? Nafka mina's? You say to me, 'I want I want
to buy you off.' According to Rabbi Akiva, I could say, 'I'm
not going to let you buy me off. It's my cow, I'm
not I'm not selling.' But according to Rabbi Yishmael, you're entitled to.
You owe me money. If you want to pay me in cash,
you're entitled to pay me in cash. Or נפקא מינה Nafka mina
is you הקדשת hikdasht it, you sold it, right? So there are
נפקא מינה's. Nafka mina's. But you're right, in a way it makes
the difference less gaping, but it makes more sense that they're not
arguing in as much of an extreme. They're both fundamentally agreeing that
if the מזיק ox isn't around, that the ניזק loses out. Yes?
And does this apply just to to loans in general, this מחלוקת?
machlokes? In other words...
No, no, specifically about this right of נזק nezek that focuses on
the מזיק ox. Right. Normally, of course, I have broad liens on
all your property and any way you owe me money. So even
if you get new property, if it's now under your possession, I
have a right to be paid my debt. But this is a
specific idea of the... right, it might be similar to גביית אפוטנקי,
gviyat apoteiki, like an אפוטנקי מפורש. apoteiki meforash. There are types of
cases where you can create a lien that is so focused that
it doesn't give me right that I lose my rights to everything
else. That's what this would be like, but it's not a standard
case. All right? All right, let's start the next פרק. perek. הדרן
עלך המניח. Hadran Alach Ha-maniach. That was definitely a very fun פרק
perek which was אדם המזיק Adam Ha-mazik and a little bit and
שור המזיק. Shor Ha-mazik. Now for for the next few פרקים, prakim,
we're going to be continuing with שור המזיק. Shor Ha-mazik. When people
think about בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, the first thing they say is
like, you know, שור שנגח את הפרה, Shor she-nagach es ha-parah, right?
Or two oxen. That's the picture that they've got on Steinsaltz, okay?
But we had a nice good three פרקים prakim or two and
a half פרקים, prakim, which was for, you know, whatever, general principles,
שן ורגל. Shen ve-Regel. I really liked the third פרק. perek. It's
a beautiful combination of אדם המזיק Adam Ha-mazik and a little bit
of בור. Bor. Remember if an אדם adam who is prone is
considered to be a בור bor or not? And then some classic
שור המזיק. Shor Ha-mazik. Now for a while we're going to be
continuing with שור המזיק, Shor Ha-mazik, okay? Goring oxen. שור שנגח ארבעה
וחמישה שוורים. Shor she-nagach arba'ah ve-chamisha shevarim. And we're going to continue
with Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yishmael. An ox gores four or five
oxen. Now it still remains a תם Tam? during this. רשי tries
to figure out if it gored four or five times, how does
it remain a תם? But basically the point is it it gored
and then it saw another ox and it didn't gore and then
it saw another one and it did, and it didn't establish a
pattern. So we'll worry about that later. But for now you'll trust
me that an ox can gore multiple times without establishing a pattern
and without being a מועד. Okay? So it's gored four or five
times. Four or five oxen. זה אחר זה. Ze achar ze. Sequentially.
ישלם לאחרון שבהם. Yeshalem le-acharon she-bahem. So the first person that gets
paid is the last person whose ox was gored. ואם יש בו
מותר, Ve-im yesh bo motar, and if there's any left over sort
of value in the goring ox, יחזיר לשלפניו, yachazir le-she-lifanav, the second
to last person. We will see. ואם יש בו מותר יחזיר לשלפני
פניו. Ve-im yesh bo motar yachazir le-she-lifnei fanav. Okay? אחרון אחרון נשכר.
Acharon acharon nishkar. Last last gored, first served. Okay? So that is
that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir.
That's what Rabbi Meir says,
right? רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: No. Rabbi Shimon's position's going
to make a lot more sense.
שור שווה מאתיים שנגח לשור שווה מאתיים ואינו יפה כלום. Shor shaveh
masayim she-nagach le-shor shaveh masayim ve-eino yafeh klum.
200 gored a 200, the carcass is worth zero. זה נוטל מנה
וזה נוטל מנה. Ze notel maneh ve-ze notel maneh. Each one becomes
now a half owner in the ox. This is Rabbi Akiva, that
you become an owner in the ox. Here's another נפקא מינה nafka
mina between Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yishmael. חזר ונגח שור אחר שווה
מאתיים. Chazar ve-nagach shor acher shaveh masayim. Then this ox gores another
one worth 200. And again the carcass is worth nothing. האחרון נוטל
מנה, ha'acharon noteil maneh, the last guy gets a hundred, 'cause that
was his damage, ושלפניו זה נוטל חמישים וזה נוטל חמישים. veshelifanav ze
noteil chamishim ve'ze noteil chamishim. And the two previous guys get 50,
right? So does everybody understand this?
Okay. Here you've got—oh, now it's X. Here you've got Reuven's ox,
okay? Reuven's ox. Shimon's one is the first one down. Okay. Everything
is going to be worth 200, okay? Fine. So now at stage
one, okay, now they both own a 100. Now it's Reuven and
Shimon's ox, okay? That was stage one. Now it gores Levi's ox,
okay? So Levi is entitled to $100, okay? His ox just got
gored by this partnered owned ox. So what do you have now?
So now Levi gets a hundred 'cause he got a hundred worth
of—I mean, he got 200 damage, he gets half, okay? So he
collects. It was owned by Reuven and Shimon, they were part owners,
so Levi is collecting from Reuven and Shimon's ox. He's collecting equally
from theirs. They were partners in that ox. So now they split
the remainder, okay? 50 and 50, right? Now it goes ahead and
it gores Yehuda's ox, okay? So Yehuda gets his full hundred. That
was gored by an ox owned by three people. Okay?
So now it stinks that as soon as a ייד Yid meets
ox you become a partner again against your will.
Right. Now תוספות Tosafot says that you have to have had the
ability to watch the ox, okay? So anyway—anyway, so then, now, if
he collects equally his hundred, so he's going to collect equally his
hundred, he's going to collect 50 from Levi,
okay, and 25 from each of those because it's going to be
equally distributed, okay? So that's what we're deal—so that's what happens. Why
25? Because he owes a hundred. This guy owns half the ox,
he owns a quarter, he owns a quarter, right? You see how
that works? So he collects his
hundred proportionately from each one of their ownership of the ox.
If you slam into my Toyota with a Porsche, I now half
owner of your Porsche?
No, up to the damage of your Toyota. Up to half the
damage of your Toyota.
But then I get the steering.
Right, exactly. Okay, so, okay. ושלפניו נוטל חמישים וזה נוטל חמישים זה.
veshelifanav noteil chamishim ve'ze noteil chamishim ze. מאתיים האחרון נוטל מנה ושלפניו
חמישים ושניים הראשונים דינר זהב. masayim ha'acharon noteil maneh veshelifanav chamishim ushenayim
harishonim dinar zahav.
The last—the first two ones get a דינר, dinar, a golden דינר,
dinar, which is 25 זוז. zuz. Now let's take a look at
תוספות Tosafot, says,
one minute. Look at the last two lines of תוספות, Tosafot I
don't want to read the beginning of תוספות Tosafot right now. But
look at the last two lines of תוספות Tosafot שור שנגח shor
shenagach by the asterisk. תוספות Tosafot says, ולא מצי לשינויי כגון שאין
בידו, velo matzi leshinuyei kegon she'ein beyado, right?
Why doesn't the גמרא Gemara say, meaning the גמרא Gemara is going
to try to figure out the first part of the משנה Mishnah
which we'll get to in a minute, but I just want to
read this. תוספות Tosafot says why don't you say that in these
cases the new owner, Shimon, Levi, they don't have liability if, you
know, if your ox was going wild and first it gored my
ox and then it ran and gored another and gored another, like
I was upstairs in my bedroom, like all of a sudden I
should be חייב chayav when it goes goring other things? So תוספות
Tosafot says you're right, in that case you're not חייב. chayav. These
cases where the new owners keep on losing out is when they
were made aware of what happened and they knew it was now
their part owner—they were part owner and they were now responsible to
watch, okay? So תוספות Tosafos says like this, he says, oh, let's
actually start a little bit higher. He says like this,
תימא, teima, לרבי עקיבא, le'Rabbi Akiva, lines up to
Rabbi Akiva, נמי אמאי אין ראשון
נזהר—why nami amai ein rishon nizhar does Shimon become responsible to watch
his portion כל זמן שלא עמד בדין? kol zman shelo amad badin?
First of all, there hasn't even been a court case. Shimon says
why am I now responsible for what it does? How do I
know I'm going actually win in court and become—and it's going to
be proven that I'm a part owner? ולא באו עדים, velo ba'u
edim, I haven't even brought witnesses תמה הוא יודע אם יזכה? tamah
hu yodeia im yizkeh? Right, so Shimon could say if I win
in court, it'll be proven that I was a part owner starting
today when your ox gored mine, but who knows if I'm even
going to win in court? וצריך לדחוס, vetzarich lidchos, you have to
say, you have to like give a bad answer or a weak
answer דכיון שיש בידו להביא עדים לאלתר, de'keivan she'yesh beyado lehavi edim
le'altar, since in theory I could bring witnesses ולזכות מתחייב בשמירתו, ulizkos
mitchayeiv bishmirato, since I know I have the ability to win in
court and I have witnesses and it technically will be proven maybe
a year from now when he finally gets out of court, it'll
be proven that I'm the owner now, my responsibility starts now. So
the first question is why am I even responsible even if I
do know about it? It hasn't been proven, I don't even know
if I'm going to win the case. And the second question is
ולא מצי לשינויי כגון שאין בידו, velo matzi leshinuyei kegon she'ein beyado,
what about if I didn't have the ability to watch it? I
was upstairs sleeping, you know, somebody called me and I was in
a different state, like wonderful, I all of a sudden automatically became
a part owner.
Maybe Once it's a court case, once it's the court case, right,
then obviously I have to
take my
steps.
Anyway תוספות Tosafos yes, it could
have said that, but anyway, for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara isn't
going there. But the reason I want you to see תוספות Tosafos
is תוספות Tosafos does make the important point that it's not like
automatically you get liability. תוספות first questions, even if you know about
it, why are you liable? You might not win in court and
whatever, and he says, well, we have to assume that you're going
to be planning on proving that you own it and that you
win in court and you have the ability, so your liability will
start now, presumably after the time it's proven, then retroactively we'll know
you were liable. But if the reality was you didn't know about
it or you didn't have the ability to watch it, obviously it's
all going to come out of ראובן's Reuven portion. It's not going
to come out of yours. You're like an אונס. oneis. You don't
have responsibility there. Yes?
You could even extend this to a case where שמעון Shimon doesn't
even know that his ox is dead yet.
Right,
absolutely. Okay, so let's see the גמרא. Now, the end case is
fun, but it's easy in a way. It's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
What's the logic of the early case that the last guy gets
full payment and anything left over goes to the second to last,
and anything left over there goes to the third to last? Like
what's the logic of that? So the גמרא says like this: מתניתין
מני? Masnisin mani? Who's our משנה? Mishna דלא כרבי ישמעאל ודלא כרבי
עקיבא. de-lo k'Rabbi Yishmael ve-lo k'Rabbi Akiva. It's not רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, it's not רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אי רבי ישמעאל דאמר בעלי
חובות נינהו, ee Rabbi Yishmael d'amar ba'alei chovos ninu, according
to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that basically it's a debt,
האי אחרון אחרון נשכר ראשון ראשון נשכר מיבעי ליה. hai achron achron
nischar, rishon rishon nischar mibayei lei. According to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
the first guy damaged has the earlier lien, the next guy has
the next lien, right? ראובן Reuven owes money to everyone. It's always
ראובן's Reuven ox. שמעון, Shimon, לוי, Levi, יהודה, Yehuda, they don't have
an ox, they just have a lien on the ox. So ראובן
Reuven owes money to all these guys and the first guy he
damages is the guy with the earlier lien. So why is the
last guy the guy to collect?
Okay, מיבעי ליה. mibayei lei. אי רבי עקיבא דאמר תורא דשותפי הוא,
ee Rabbi Akiva d'amar tura de-shutfey hu, if it's like רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, it's partnered, האי יש בו מותר יחזרו לשל לפניו, hai
yesh bo motar yachzeru le-shel le-fanav, why do we see if there's
anything left it goes to the second-to-last guy? לכולם מיבעי ליה. le-chulom
mibayei lei. No, it gets distributed to all of them. I mean,
it is true according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, like the second-to-last
guy gets a bigger portion, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva excuse me, but
it does get distributed to all. It's not that the entire remainder
goes to the second-to-last guy. Okay, אמר רבא. amar Rava. So that's
the question: what the heck is the first part of the משנה?
אמר רבא amar Rava says רבא: Rava:
לעולם כרבי ישמעאל. le-olam k'Rabbi Yishmael. The משנה is רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, דאמר בעלי חובות נינהו, d'amar ba'alei chovos ninu, that it's a
debt. ודקשיא לך אחרון אחרון נשכר ראשון ראשון נשכר מיבעי ליה? ve-de-kasha
lach achron achron nischar, rishon rishon nischar mibayei lei? You want to
know why the last guy has rights, it should be the first
guy that has the most rights. היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachat la?
כגון שתפס ניזק לגבות הימנו ונעשה לו כשומר שכר לניזקין. kegon she-tafas
nizak ligbos heimenu ve-na'asa lo ke-shomer sachar le-nezikin. So the case here
is for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, okay, so this is רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, for רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, for רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
the case was, okay, it gored שמעון's Shimon ox and then שמעון
Shimon said, 'Ah, I have a lien on that ox.' If I
have a lien on that ox, I'm going to back תפס. I'm
going to grab it and take it, and it's not mine yet
because it's just money owed to me. I have to get it,
you know, processed in court, but I'm basically, I'm like holding on
to your property as collateral. I have a right on that ox,
I'm going to take possession of it, bring it into my property
so that you don't run away with it, so that I'll be
able to collect my loan off of it. Since I am holding
on to a piece of property that I have a lien on
and I'm holding on to it as collateral, I become a שומר
שכר. shomer sachar. I become, I'm getting שכר. sachar. Why am I
getting שכר? sachar? Because my payment is that I'm getting the benefit
of knowing that I'll be able to collect from it. I've taken
possession of your thing that I'm getting benefit from having possession of
it, and therefore I'm a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. And a שומר
שכר shomer sachar means I'm liable not only to you, but I
also become liable if it goes and it damages somebody else. Okay?
So because שמעון Shimon took possession, he becomes a שומר שכר. shomer
sachar. Now this ox goes ahead and it gores לוי's Levi ox.
Okay? So שמעון Shimon is the one that is now fully liable.
Right? If I give my ox over to a שומר, shomer, I
don't become liable, the שומר shomer is fully liable. So לוי Levi
collects his full amount from שמעון's Shimon right portion in the ox.
Okay? And that's why שמעון Shimon is out. Now לוי Levi seizes
it and then it goes ahead and gores יהודה's Yehuda ox. So
יהודה Yehuda collects his full portion from לוי. Levi. If there was
anything left, whatever's left belongs to לוי. Levi. Okay? Right?
Because לוי Levi was collecting it from שמעון. Shimon. If there's anything
left, etc. So that's how it works.
I know. Okay, so let's continue. So it says like this: אי
הכי ee hachi says the גמרא, but one minute, it doesn't really
fully work. יש בו מותר יחזרו לשל לפניו
יחזרו לבעלים מיבעי ליה. yesh bo motar yachzeru shel le-fanav, yachzeru le-ba'alim
mibayei lei. If there's anything left over, why does it go to
לוי? Levi? It should go all the way back to ראובן. Reuven.
What?
Doesn't this just mean it's a cycle? Everyone, as much further back
you can go, you go.
No, because if we're assuming it is that... Let's assume, let's assume
that the damage is the same. Let's assume it was a $200
ox, okay? And there was $100 worth of damage, right? So if
he went ahead and he seized it, he had $100 rights to
it, okay? And now he goes ahead and his ox got damaged,
his worth 100, he's totally took over שמעון's Shimon amount, so anything
left goes back to ראובן, Reuven, right? Let's say it was a
$300 ox, okay? So he got $100 worth of damage, okay, he
seized it, alright, so he has now rights of 100 and the
other 200 still belongs to ראובן. Reuven. He damages this, he has
rights of 100, he takes שמעון's Shimon part, the remainder goes to
ראובן. Reuven. He got damaged 100, he takes לוי's Levi part who
took שמעון's Shimon part, so they're all swapping the same original 100,
but the remainder part all goes back to ראובן. Reuven. Right, is
that clear? Alright, right? Whatever I get, I'm losing to the next
guy and I can lose to the next guy, but anything that
wasn't taken goes back ultimately to the original owner.
Then what's if that the third, whatever, the second goring is only
50?
Right, so that's the גמרא's going to say. Okay, so the גמרא's
going to say, okay, אמר רבינא הכא תני אם יש מותר בניזקיו
יחזיר לשלפניו. Amar Ravina Hacha Tani, Im Yesh Motar BiNizakav, Yachzir LiShelFanaiv.
Okay,
if there's leftover money in the damage, meaning, so basically, let's say,
right, שמעון's Shimon thing was damaged 300,
לוי's Levi thing was damaged 200, and יהודה's Yehuda was damaged 100,
okay? So therefore שמעון Shimon now became owner of 150. לוי, Levi,
whose was damaged 200, he became owner of 100, so there's now,
he has 100, there's leftover because of the different degree of damage,
so he took 100 of שמעון's Shimon 150 and the extra 50
went back to שמעון. Shimon. Are you with me? שמעון Shimon had
a bigger damage, שמעון Shimon was entitled to 150. He was only
entitled to 100. So he got 100 out of שמעון's Shimon 150
and שמעון Shimon kept the remaining 50. He only got 50. So
he got 50 out of לוי's Levi 100. Okay, לוי Levi had
50 left and he took it out of whatever. So because the
damages are more here, they're getting everybody's taking from everybody else's piece
of the pie. Okay, but if you have a bigger piece of
the pie and then you get a smaller damage and a smaller
piece, any part of your pie that was left over you get
to keep.
So that's the גמרא's question, why doesn't it go all the way
back to the original?
It does. The 150 that was originally ראובן's Reuven that was never
seized by שמעון Shimon as it were, ראובן Reuven is always going
to get, okay? But the amount their parts of the pie, if
it's increasingly smaller pieces, then they're leaving over to the people from
before them.
And I still don't see how this can be a תם. How
could this possibly be a תם?
Why not? Because it gored multiple times? Yeah, I said that in
the beginning. There, there are ways in which it does, it sees
other animals and it doesn't gore them so it never gets to
be habitual.
Yeah, but in the meantime other animals are walking around.
Right. Okay, so let's just read another line here. וכן כי אתא
רבינא אמר רבי יוחנן משום שליחות שמים נגעו בה. VeChen ki ata
Ravina Amar Rabbi Yochanan MiShum Shlihut Shomim Nagu Bah. The problem here
is that you become a שומר Shomer and that's why the next
party becomes liable and that's why it works according to רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Ishmael, but you don't automatically become liable, you have to seize
it and become a שומר. Shomer. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this, אי הכי, I Hachi, if that's true, אימא סיפא. Ei Ma
Seifa. רבי שמעון אומר שור שוה מאתים שנגח שור שוה מאתים ואין
לו לזה אלא יפה כלום זה נוטל מנה וזה נוטל מנה. Rabbi
Shimon Omer Shor Shaveh Matayim SheNagash Shor Shaveh Matayim VeEin Lo LeZeh
Ela Yafeh Klum Zeh Notel Maneh VeZeh Notel Maneh. חזר ונגח שור
אחר שוה מאתים האחרון נוטל מנה ושלפניו נוטל חמשים זוז וזה וזה
נוטלין חמשים זוז. Chazar VeNagash Shor Acher Shaveh Matayim HaAharon Notel Maneh
VeShelFanaiv Notel Hamishim Zuz VeZeh VeZeh Notlin Hamishim Zuz. This goes very
quick because we're just quoting the משנה. חזר ונגח שור שוה מאתים
האחרון נוטל מנה ושלפניו נוטל חמשים זוז ושנים הראשונים דינר זהב. Chazar
VeNagash Shor Shaveh Matayim HaAharon Notel Maneh VeShelFanaiv Notel Hamishim Zuz VeShnayim
HaRishonim Dinur Zahav. Okay, so the,
so fine, you explained the beginning was רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael was
talking about seizing it, but the end is clearly רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, everybody becomes partners. So אתיא לרבי עקיבא, Ata LaRabbi Akiva, that's
goes like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דאמר תורא דשותפי הוא, DeAmar Tora
DeShutfei Hu, that they're partners.
רישא רבי ישמעאל וסיפא רבי עקיבא? Reisha Rabbi Ishmael VeSeifa Rabbi Akiva?
Is that possible? Now it's a funny question because, yeah, they're different
תנאים, Tannaim, one is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the other is
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, right, רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Okay, so sure,
but the problem is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon are both תלמידים Talmidim of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so it
is a little bit funny that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is siding
with רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon with רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But at least they are different תנאים. Tannaim. So
the גמרא says, is that possible? אמרי אין, Amri In, yes,
דהא אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה שיננא סרפון שבוק מתניתין ותא בתראי,
DeHa Amar Lei Shmuel LeRav Yehuda Shinana Sarpun Shevok Matnitan VeTa Batrai,
don't let the משנה bother you and just follow me. רישא רבי
ישמעאל וסיפא רבי עקיבא. Reisha Rabbi Ishmael VeSeifa Rabbi Akiva. Okay? So
yes, so that's what it is. The end where they become partners
and it's a hundred and fifty-fifty or whatever, you know, 100, 50,
25, 25 or whatever, that's all רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that's partners.
This idea where the last guy gets and then whatever's left gets
bumped up, that's a case of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael where it
was seized and you became a שומר Shomer and therefore you can
lose your portion to the guy after you. All right? So we've
explained the משנה and we will pick up with a different point
tomorrow. Wow. Wow. Yeah, so we actually did a pretty good job.